

# Igor Shalyminov

E-mail: ishalyminov@gmail.com

Phone: +447514863061

Website: <a href="https://linkedin.com/in/ishalyminov">https://linkedin.com/in/ishalyminov</a>

Address: School of Mathematical

and Computer Sciences, Heriot-Watt University Edinburgh EH14 4AS United Kingdom

## About me

I'm a PhD student at the Heriot-Watt University under the supervision of Prof. Oliver Lemon and Dr. Arash Eshghi. My research interests are in the areas of Natural Language Processing and Machine Learning. My research is focused on spoken dialogue systems, and its main goal is bringing the level of domain-restrictedness of such systems as well as the amount human supervision required to the minimum.

## Education

## PhD, Computer Science

October 2016 — Present

Heriot-Watt University

Research area: Deep learning methods for spoken dialogue systems

Supervisors: Prof. Oliver Lemon, Dr. Arash Eshghi

## Professional Retraining in Data Analysis (MSc equiv.)

September 2010 — June 2012

Yandex School of Data Analysis (Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology)

Computer Science Department

GPA: 4,66

## Specialist (MSc equiv.)

September 2005 — June 2010

Moscow State University of Instrument Engineering and Computer Science Information Technologies Department

Major: Computing machines, systems, and networks

GPA: 5,0

Defended thesis "A module for generating data for equipment reliability estimation in the 'Prognosis' software suite"

Supervisor: Prof. Aleksandr Aleksandrov

## **Awards**

Dialogue System Technology Challenge (DSTC) 8, Fast Domain Adaptation - 1st place, 2019 EMNLP 2019 - Student Travel Scholarship, 2019

SCAI workshop@EMNLP 2018 - travel grant from sponsors (Microsoft, Facebook, Google, and TextKernel), 2018 Amazon Alexa Prize 2018 (part of team Alana) - 3rd place prize + research grant, 2018

Amazon Alexa Prize 2017 (part of team Alana) - 3rd place prize + research grant, 2017 James Watt Scholarship from Heriot-Watt University, 2016

## Work experience

### Microsoft Research Montréal

May 2019 — August 2019

Research Intern

Mentor: Dr. Hannes Schulz

Project: Dialogue State Tracking Challenge (DSTC) 8 - Fast Domain Adaptation

## Microsoft AI and Research

Jun 2018 — Sep 2018

Research Intern

Mentor: Dr. Sungjin Lee

Project title: "Improving robustness of goal-oriented dialog systems in an unsupervised way".

## Yandex LLC, Moscow

August 2013 — September 2016

Software Engineer

Projects I participated in:

- Voice interfaces for applications dialogue management module
- · Voice analytics for callcenters search engine for voice data
- Russian National Corpus search engine for linguistic research

# Yandex School of Data Analysis (Yandex LLC / Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology), Moscow

September 2013 — June 2015

**Teaching Assistant** 

Natural Language Processing course taught by Dr. Alexey Zobnin (Computer Science department, final year course).

My resposibilities for the course were:

- · designing problems for the seminar classes;
- conducting the classes;
- helping the professor with designing home assignments and reviewing students' submissions.

## Microsoft Corporation, Redmond

May 2014 — August 2014

Research Intern

Mentors: Dr. Yuxiong He, Dr. Sameh Elnikety

I worked on a query optimizer for a term distributed search engine. During my internship, I completed the following tasks:

- built combined analytical and statistical models of a search query for estimating its latency and amount of data for network communication;
- designed and implemented algorithms for producing optimal query plans in terms of minimizing either of the two objectives: latency or network communication.

The prototype of the guery optimizer and distributed experimental platform was implemented in Java and Python.

## Yandex LLC, Moscow

May 2012 — August 2013

Junior Software Engineer

Participated in development of Russian National Corpus . I maintained the search engine at its existing architecture and explored the possibilities of improving it for better performance and reliability.

Software Engineer Intern

Mentor: Dr. Alexey Zobnin

Built a prototype of an N-gram search service for Russian National Corpus. The service consisted of two components:

- N-grams storage a compressed delta-encoded word trie written in C++;
- Search client an http server in Python receiving user requests and fetching the results from the N-gram storage.

## Intel Corporation

June 2010 — August 2010

Software Engineer Intern

Mentor: Dr. Denis Makoshenko

As a part of Intel Summer School 2010, I participated in Intel C/C++ Compiler development with a research project "Enhancing the methodology to access the bottom boundary of software pipelined cycle execution time as the application of an algorithm for finding a maximum cycle in a directed graph".

## Moscow State University of Instrument Engineering and Computer Science

2006 - 2012

Software Engineer

Participated in the development of "Prognosis" - a software suite for reliability calculation of the equipment used in nuclear energetics.

## Additional Education

#### Summer Schools attended:

- 2013 Microsoft School on Algorithms for Massive Data (ALMADA). Attended lectures on the effective algorithms
  for External Memory computational model, algorithms and techniques for large-scale graph problems. Did
  theoretical assignments on graph algorithms and a Linq programming assignment in Linq.
- 2011 Yandex Summer School On Distributed Computing. Attended lectures on Information Retrieval and MapReduce computing model. Did a practice assignment in Hadoop.
- 2010 Intel Summer School. Attended lectures and webinars on parallel computing and processor architectures. Learned Intel IA64 architecture (Itanium I and II), participated in Intel C++ Compiler development.

#### University Courses Taken:

 2014 - Formal Semantics and Typology of Anaphora taught by Barbara H Partee. National Research University Higher School Of Economics

#### MOOCs Taken:

- Bayesian Statistics: Techniques and Models Coursera (2019)
- Bayesian Statistics: From Concept to Data Analysis Coursera (2019)
- Bayesian Methods for Machine Learning Coursera (2018)
- Deep Learning Specialization Coursera (2018)
- Neural Networks For Machine Learning Coursera (2017)
- Artificial Intelligence for Robotics Udacity (2016)
- Deep Learning Udacity (2016)
- Machine Learning: Reinforcement Learning Udacity (2015)
- Intro to Artificial Intelligence Udacity (2013)
- Intro To Statistics Udacity (2012)

#### Certifications:

- Microsoft Certified Professional 70-536 Microsoft .NET Application Development Foundation
- Electronic office programmer C++ and Pascal programming (Specialist Training Centre)

## **Tests Taken**

- TOEFL iBT: 99 (Reading 26, Listening 24, Speaking 24, Writing 25)
- GRE: Verbal Reasoning 152, Quantitative Reasoning 161, Analytical Writing 4.0
- IELTS Academic UKVI: 8.0 (Listening 8.5, Reading 8.5, Writing 7.5, Speaking 7.0)

## Language Ability

- Russian native;
- English upper-intermediate;
- · Spanish beginner

## Relevant Skills

### **Programming Languages**

Python, C++, Java, Perl

#### **Frameworks**

Tensorflow, scikit-learn, Keras, Lucene

#### **Databases**

mongodb, MySQL

#### Data analysis tools

Jupyter notebook, matplotlib, pandas

#### **Core Technical Skills**

Strong knowledge of classic algorithms and data structures; strong mathematical foundation; knowledge of machine learning algorithms; backgound in Natural Language Processing

## **Interests**

Foreign languages, healthy lifestyle, photography, electronic music production.

## References

Prof. Oliver Lemon

Professor, School of Mathematical & Computer Sciences, Heriot-Watt University

Email: o.lemon@hw.ac.uk

Arash Eshghi, PhD

Assistant Professor, School of Mathematical & Computer Sciences, Heriot-Watt University

Email: a.eshghi@hw.ac.uk

Sungjin Lee, PhD

Senior Researcher, Microsoft Research

Email: sule@microsoft.com

Yuxiong He, PhD Researcher, Microsoft Research Email: yuxhe@microsoft.com

## **Publications**

#### 2019

- Igor Shalyminov, Sungjin Lee, Arash Eshghi, Oliver Lemon. Data-Efficient Goal-Oriented Conversation with Dialogue Knowledge Transfer Networks. EMNLP 2019
- Igor Shalyminov, Sungjin Lee, Arash Eshghi, Oliver Lemon. Few-Shot Dialogue Generation Without Annotated Data: A Transfer Learning Approach. SigDial 2019
- Sungjin Lee and Igor Shalyminov. Contextual Out of domain Utterance Handling with Counterfeit Data Augmentation. ICASSP 2019

#### 2018

- Igor Shalyminov and Sungjin Lee. Improving Robustness of Neural Dialog Systems in a Data-Efficient Way with Turn Dropout. NeurIPS 2018 workshop on Conversational AI
- Igor Shalyminov, Arash Eshghi, and Oliver Lemon. Multi-Task Learning for Domain-General Spoken Disfluency Detection in Dialogue Systems. SemDial 2018
- Igor Shalyminov, Ondrej Dusek, and Oliver Lemon. Neural Response Ranking for Social Conversation: A Data-Efficient Approach. Search-Oriented Conversational AI, an EMNLP 2018 Workshop
- Amanda Cercas Curry, Ioannis Papaioannou, Alessandro Suglia, Shubham Agarwal, Igor Shalyminov, Xinnuo Xu, Ondřej Dušek, Arash Eshghi, Ioannis Konstas, Verena Rieser and Oliver Lemon. Alana v2: Entertaining and Informative Open-domain Social Dialogue using Ontologies and Entity Linking. Alexa Prize proceedings, 2018

#### 2017

- Igor Shalyminov, Arash Eshghi, and Oliver Lemon. Challenging Neural Dialogue Models with Natural Data: Memory Networks Fail on Incremental Phenomena. SemDial 2017
- Arash Eshghi, Igor Shalyminov, and Oliver Lemon. Bootstrapping incremental dialogue systems from minimal data: the generalisation power of semantic grammars. EMNLP 2017
- Arash Eshghi, Igor Shalyminov, and Oliver Lemon. Bootstrapping Dialogue Systems: Using a Semantic Model of Dialogue to Generalise from Minimal Data. LaML 2017
- Arash Eshghi, Igor Shalyminov, and Oliver Lemon. Interactional Dynamics and the Emergence of Language Games. FADLI 2017
- Ioannis Papaioannou, Amanda Cercas Curry, Jose L. Part, Igor Shalyminov, Xinnuo Xu, Yanchao Yu, Ondrej Dušek, Verena Rieser, Oliver Lemon. Alana: Social Dialogue using an Ensemble Model and a Ranker trained on User Feedback. 2017 Alexa Prize Proceedings
- Ioannis Papaioannou, Amanda Cercas Curry, Jose L. Part, Igor Shalyminov, Xinnuo Xu, Yanchao Yu, Ondrej Dušek, Verena Rieser, Oliver Lemon. An Ensemble Model with Ranking for Social Dialogue. NIPS Workshop on Conversational AI 2017

#### 2010

• Igor Shalyminov. Using Policies in Designing of a Library for Cell Operations in 'Prognoz' Software Package. Software for PC-based systems for various purposes #13, pp. 101–107. ISBN 978-5-8068-0462-5

#### 2009

• Igor Shalyminov. Algorithms for calculation of constructions fault probability in 'Prognoz' software package. Applied Mathematics and Mathematical Modelling, pp. 70–77. ISBN 978-5-8122-1023-6

#### 2008

 Aleksandr Aleksandrov, Alexey Vostrikov, and Igor Shalyminov. An algorithm for generation geometric objects for crack formation analysis. Software for PC-based systems for various purposes #11, pp. 145–148. ISBN 978-5-8068-0418-2

#### 2007

 Aleksandr Aleksandrov and Igor Shalyminov. An algorithm for definition of crack formation probability in statistical modeling. Software for PC-based systems for various purposes #10, pp. 11–15. ISBN 978-5-8068-0393-2

## **Professional Service**

Program committee: AAAI 2020, SCAI@IJCAI 2019, ACL 2019, ACL 2018 (last-minute reviewer), COLING 2018, EMNLP 2018 (secondary reviewer), SCAI@EMNLP 2018